Zhonghao (Jonathan) Shi

CONTACT Information $1120~\mathrm{W}$ 6th Street Los Angeles, CA 90017

Mobile: (213)-666-6078 Email: zhonghas@usc.edu

RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research focuses on developing intelligent agents that can learn from, reason about, and interact with the real world by leveraging heterogeneous, noisy, and imperfect information from human-centered environments. More specifically, I work on: 1) designing and developing socially assistive robotic systems that can help people with special needs such as children with ASD; 2) applying machine learning and deep learning to enable human activity recognition in human-human/human-computer/human-robot interaction; 3) using reinforcement learning and multi-armed bandit algorithms to allow real-time personalization of interaction based on users' preferences.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Human-Computer Interaction, Robotics (Human-Robot Interaction), Computer Vision, Multimodal Machine Learning, Socially Assistive Robotics (SAR), Human Activity Recognition, Personalized Affective Computing, Assistive Educational Technology

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Computer Science, University of Southern California (USC)

– Research Advisor: Professor Maja J. Matarić

- GPA: 4.00/4.00 Expected Dec 2024

BSc, Computer Science, University of Southern California (USC)

- Research Advisor: Professor Maja J. Matarić

- GPA: 4.00/4.00 Aug 2017 - May 2020

BEng, Electronic and Electrical Engineering, University College London (UCL)

- Academic Advisor: Professor Martyn Fice

- GPA: 3.89/4.00 Sep 2015 - May 2017 (transferred)

Work Experience

USC Interaction Lab

Ph.D. Research Assistant, Los Angeles, CA Advised by Professor Maja J. Matarić May 2020 - Present

- Human-Computer/Human-Robot Interaction: Developing an open-sourced socially assistive robot platform using the blossom robot with real-time multimodal sensing and socially interactive capabilities [github]; applying multi-armed bandit with correlated arms algorithms to enable preference personalization in social human-robot interaction settings [github]
- Computer Vision: Working on developing skeleton-based action recognition models with multimodal data for indoor human-human/human-computer/human-robot interaction
- Applied Multimodal Machine Learning Applied supervised/unsupervised domain adaptation to design personalized supervised machine learning models outperforming non-personalized baselines for affective recognition to detect cognitive affective states for children with ASD [github, paper]; Applied supervised machine learning methods to model user engagement from children with ASD [paper]

J.P.Morgan Chase & Co.

Summer Research Associate, New York, NY

Jun 2022 - August 2022

- Working on applied machine learning projects with the aim of introducing and validating novel artificial intelligence research solutions in scientific publications.

USC Interaction Lab

Undergraduate Research Assistant, Los Angeles, CA
Advised by Professor Maja J. Matarić

Jan 2018 - May 2020

- VR/AR and Robotics Integrated ROS into Unity 3D's C# environment along with software engineering using the Mixed Reality Toolkit for the Microsoft Hololens [paper]
- Applied Machine Learning: Trained both normal and individualized Bayesian Knowledge Tracing models to study the learning curves for individual participant with autism after studying with our socially assistive robot math tutor [paper]
- Applied Machine Learning: Developed a multimodal data processing pipeline to synchronize and synthesize a multimodal dataset collected from in-home SAR deployments

ARM Holdings

Computer Engineering Intern, Cambridge, United Kingdom Jun 2017 - July 2017

- Designed real-time operating system (RTOS) coursework in C on micro-controller Nucleo F401RE as part of the ARM University Program
- Documented RTOS education kit for ARM University Program

London Centre for Nanotechnology

Research Intern, Cambridge, United Kingdom

Aug 2016 - Sep 2016

- Tested and validated the PCB board design for the open-source atomic force microscope (openAFM) project
- Translated design team's UX mockups into responsive, interactive features, using HTML/CSS and JavaScript

PUBLICATIONS:
* INDICATES CO-FIRST AUTHOR
REFEREED
JOURNAL
ARTICLES

- Shi, Z., Groechel, T.R., Jain, S., Chima, K., Rudovic, O. and Matarić, M.J., 2021. Toward Personalized Affect-Aware Socially Assistive Robot Tutors in Long-Term Interventions for Children with Autism. ACM Transactions of Human-Robot Interaction (THRI).
- [2] Jain, S., Thiagarajan, B., Shi, Z., Clabaugh, C. and Matarić, M.J., 2020. Modeling engagement in long-term, in-home socially assistive robot interventions for children with autism spectrum disorders. Science Robotics, 5(39).
- [3] Clabaugh, C., Mahajan, K., Jain, S., Pakkar, R., Becerra, D., **Shi, Z.**, Deng, E., Lee, R., Ragusa, G. and Matarić, M.J., 2019. Long-term personalization of an in-home socially assistive robot for children with autism spectrum disorders. *Frontiers in Robotics and AI*, 6, p.110.

REFEREED CONFERENCE PAPERS

- [4] Zhou, E.*, **Shi, Z.***, Qiao, X., Matarić, M.J. and Bittner A.K., 2021. Designing a Socially Assistive Robot to Support Older Adults with Low Vision. Proceedings of the 2021 International Conference on Social Robotics (ICSR).
- [5] Groechel, T., Shi, Z., Pakkar, R. and Matarić, M.J., 2019, October. Using socially expressive mixed reality arms for enhancing low-expressivity robots. Proceedings of the 2019 28th IEEE International Conference on Robot and Human Interactive Communication (RO-MAN) (pp. 1-8). IEEE.
- [6] Clabaugh, C., Jain, S., Thiagarajan, B., Shi, Z., Mathur, L. and Mahajan, K., 2018. Attentiveness of children with diverse needs to a socially assistive robot in the home. Proceedings of the 2018 International Symposium on Experimental Robotics.

REFEREED WORKSHOP OR SHORT PAPERS

- [7] Chen, H.*, **Shi, Z.***, Dennler, N., Humber, N. and Matarić, M.J., 2021. Your Voice of Mindfulness: Evaluating and Personalizing Text-to-Speech Voices for Mindfulness Practice 2022 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA 2022) Workshop on Sound for Robots.
- [8] Shi, Z. and Matarić, M.J., 2022. Recognizing Fine-Grained Cognitive-Affective Behaviors of Children with Autism Spectrum Disorder. Accepted in International Society for Research on Emotion conference.
- [9] Shi, Z., Cao, M., Pei, S., Tarbox, J.J. and Matarić, M.J., 2021. Toward Personalized Automated Annotation of Targeted Behaviors of Children with ASD in Robot-Assisted ABA Interventions. Proceedings of the 2021 Virtual Conference of Technology, Mind, and Behavior. APA.
- [10] Shi, Z., Pei, S., Qiao X., Groechel T.R. and Matarić, M.J., 2021. Personalized Affect-Aware Socially Assistive Robot Tutors Aimed at Fostering Social Grit in Children with Autism. ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human Robot Interaction (HRI) Workshop on Child-Robot Interaction and Child's Fundamental Rights.

Honors and Awards

USC Robotics George Bekey Service Award	May 2021
USC Computer Science Award for Outstanding Research	May 2020
USC Computer Science Outstanding Student Award	May~2020
USC Provost Award (Top 1% of the Graduating Class)	May~2020
USC Provost's Undergraduate Research Fellowship	Aug~2020
USC Undergraduate Research Symposium First Award	Apr~2019
UCL Goldsmid Prize for Outstanding Students (Top 3 of the Class)	May 2017

STUDENT RESEARCH MENTORING

Students

Judelius	
– Sophia Pei	Computational Biology, USC Undergraduate Student
– Lydia DiBlasio	Computer Science, USC Undergraduate Student
– Han Chen	Computer Science, USC Undergraduate Student
– Natalie Humber	Computer Science, USC Undergraduate Student
- Martin Liu	Computer Science, USC Undergraduate Student
– Flora Jia	Computer Science, USC Undergraduate Student
– Eunsook (Victoria) S	hin Computer Science, USC Undergraduate Student
– Maÿlis Whetsel Co	omputer Science, Columbia University Undergraduate Student
- Amanda Yao	Computer Science, UC Berkeley Undergraduate Student
– Riya Ranjan	SHINE program, High School Student
– Anishka Raina	SHINE program, High School Student
- Allen Wang	SHINE program, High School Student

SERVICE

Reviewer

- MDPI AI 2022
- IEEE International Conference on Robot Human Interactive Communication (RO-MAN) 2022
- International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2021
- MDPI Brain Sciences 2020
- International Journal of Human-Computer Interaction 2020

K-12 EDUCATIONAL OUTREACH

Robotics Family Night

Monterey Hills Elementary, South Pasadena, CA The Help Group STEM³ Academy Visit STEM³ Academy, Los Angeles, CA

May 2019. Nov 2019

Jun 2019

USC Remote Robotics Open House

USC, Los Angeles, CA May 2020

Computer Science: Deep Learning, Advanced Computer Vision, Robotics, Machine Relevant Coursework Learning for Data Science, Computational Human-Robot Interaction, Applied Natural

Language Processing, Multimodal Learning of Human Communication

Electronic Engineering: Digital Electronics, Analog Electronics, Control System

TECHNICAL Languages: Python, Java, Javascript, C/C++, C#, Bash, SQL, HTML, CSS SKILLS

Libraries and Tools: Pytorch, MXNET, OpenCV, Tensorflow, Robot Operating Sys-

tem (ROS), Numpy, Pandas, Seaborn, Scikit-Learn, Hadoop/HBase, Git

4 of 4